A Finding Aid to the B. C. Holland Gallery Records, 1942-1991, bulk 1959-1965, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
B. C. Holland Gallery records
1942-1991
bulk 1959-1965
Archives of American Art
B.C. Holland Gallery
Holland, B. C. (Bud C.), 1922-1994
AAA.bcholl
Archival Resource Key
2.1 Linear feet
The records of the B. C. Holland Gallery measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1942-1991 (bulk dates 1959-1965). Founded in Chicago, Illinois by Bud C. Holland and Noah Goldowsky, the collection documents over 98 artists associated with the gallery. Documentation includes invoices, correspondence between artists and gallery owners, price lists, exhibition catalogs and print materials, magazine and newspaper clippings, photographs, and slides, and some business records of the gallery.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Artist files, 1942-1991 (2.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, OV 3)
Series 2: Business records, 1961-1963 (1 folder; Box 2)
Biographical / Historical
B. C. Holland Gallery (1957-1994) was founded by Bud C. Holland and Noah Goldowsky, and was initially known as the Holland-Goldowsky Gallery. It held exhibitions and sold artwork for Chicago artists and many artists of the New York School. Holland bought out his partner and renamed the gallery the B. C. Holland Gallery in August 1961. The gallery closed upon Holland's death in 1994.
Bud C. Holland entered the jewelry business, after serving in WWII as a bomber pilot, where he began collecting artwork. He opened his first art gallery in 1957. During the 1960s pop trend, Holland was drawn towards abstract expressionism and other art forms, which he focused on in his gallery. He began selling his collection when he was diagnosed with cancer, and died at 72 in Chicago, Illinois, 29 December 1994.
Scope and Contents
The records of the B. C. Holland Gallery measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1942-1991 (bulk dates 1959-1965). Founded in Chicago, Illinois by Bud C. Holland and Noah Goldowsky, the collection documents over 98 artists associated with the gallery. Documentation includes invoices, correspondence between artists and gallery owners, price lists, exhibition catalogues and print materials, magazine and newspaper clippings, photographs, and slides, and some business records of the gallery.
Artists of note include: Harry Bouras, Paul Burlin, Mary Callery, Elaine de Kooning, Willem de Kooning, Jean Dubuffet, Edward Dugmore, Roland Ginzel (including 2 ink drawings), Michael Goldberg, Robert Goodnough, Joseph Goto, Philip Guston, Julius Hatofsky, Richard Hunt (includes 18 files and a landscape plan of John J. Madden Clinic sculpture installation), Lester Johnson, Ellen Lanyon, Alfred Leslie, Jacques Lipchitz, Michael Loew, Knox Martin, Dennis Oppenheim, Stephen Pace, Milton Resnick, Larry Rivers, Aaron Siskind, George Spaventa, Saul Steinberg, Jack Tworkov, and Estaban Vicente.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The B. C. Holland Gallery records were donated to the Archives of American Art by Bud C. Holland's widow, Claire Y. Holland, in 1995.
Photographs; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Artists -- Illinois -- Chicago; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- United States; Art galleries, Commercial -- Illinois; De Kooning, Willem, 1904-1997; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-; Dugmore, Edward, 1915-; Ginzel, Roland, 1921-; Bouras, Harry; Burlin, Paul, 1886-1969; Callery, Mary, 1903-1977; De Kooning, Elaine; Holland-Goldowsky Gallery; Goldberg, Michael, 1924-2007; Goodnough, Robert, 1917-; Goto, Joseph, 1920-; Guston, Philip, 1913-1980; Hatofsky, Jerry, 1922-; Leslie, Alfred, 1927-; Oppenheim, Dennis, 1938-2011; Pace, Stephen, 1918-2010; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973; Loew, Michael, 1907-1985; Spaventa, George, 1918-; Siskind, Aaron; Resnick, Milton, 1917-2004; Rivers, Larry, 1925-2002; Vicente, Esteban, 1903-2001; Tworkov, Jack; Goldowsky, Noah; Johnson, Lester, 1919-2010; Lanyon, Ellen; Steinberg, Saul; Hunt, Richard, 1935-
- Artist Files, 1942-1991; bulk 1959-1965; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Found here are invoices, correspondence between artists and gallery owners, price lists, exhibition catalogues and exhibition print materials, magazine and newspaper clippings, black and white and color photographs, slides, negatives, 2 pieces of artwork, and 1 landscape plan. There are two files containing letters of authenticity and invoices for Gandaharan sculptures, a style of Buddhist art from the Kushan period dating between 1st and 5th centuries A.D., and Haniwa, a style of Japanese sculpture made using the wasumi technique in the Kofun period between 4th and 6th centuries A.D. Correspondence during 1957 and 1961 may include Noah Goldowsky, co-owner of the Holland-Goldowsky Gallery until 1961. Also note that some artist files may contain a single item.
  - Agam, Yaacov, 1963-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albers, Josef, 1963-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arman, Armand Pierre, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Balthus Klossowski de Rola, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beal, Sondra, 1962-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berlant, Anthony, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berlet, Marc, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bluhm, Norman, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bouras, Harry, 1959-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Brandt, Warren, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Breland, Bruce, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Burlin, Paul, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Callahan, Harry, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Callery, Mary - Correspondence, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Callery, Mary - Photographs, Catalog, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Caro, Anthony, 1961-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Corbett, Ed, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Decker, Lindsey, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - De Kooning, Elaine, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - De Kooning, Willem, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - DeLap, Tony, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dubuffet, Jean, 1968-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dugmore, Edward, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Ellsworth, David, 1983-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Eversley, Frederick, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gandharan, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ginzel, Roland, 1961-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    (Oversized material housed in OV 3)
  - Goldberg, Elias, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Goldberg, Michael, 1959-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Goldberg, Michael, 1959-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Goodnough, Robert, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gore, Bert, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Goto, Joseph, 1973-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grillo, John, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Guston, Philip, 1958-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Haniwa, 1958-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hatofsky, Julius, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hedge, Gene, 1961-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Herschler, David, 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Howard, Al, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hubbard, Robert, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hunt, Richard - Correspondence, 1961-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49-57)
  - Hunt, Richard - Photographs of Hunt and his artwork, 1967-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hunt, Richard - Resumes, Price Lists, circa 1963-circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hunt, Richard - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60-61)
  - Hunt, Richard - Clippings, 1961-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62-65)
  - Hunt, Richard - Printed Material, 1961-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Ippolito, Angelo, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Jannes, Georgia, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Johnson, Lester, 1961-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69-72)
  - Kadish, Reuben, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Kerkam, Earl, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Kohn, Gabriel, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Kohn, Misch, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Kostka, Robert, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Kusama, Yayoi, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Kuwayama, Tadaaki, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Lanyon, Ellen, 1963-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 80-81)
  - Leslie, Alfred - Correspondence, 1959-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 82-84)
  - Leslie, Alfred - Resumes, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Leslie, Alfred - Printed Material, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Levee, John, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Lewis, Golda, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Lince, Richard, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Loew, Michael, 1960-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Martin, Knox, 1957-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miller, Richard, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mischo, Ivan, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miro, Juan, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell, Joan, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Monaghan, Brian, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Morandi, Giorgio, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nakian, Reuben, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newbili, Al, 1960-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Nickle, Robert, 1963-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Oppenheim, Dennis, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Oppenheim, Dennis - Photographs of Artwork, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pace, Stephen, 1954-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Pavia, Phillip, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pfriem, Bernard, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Resnick, Milton - Correspondence, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - Resnick, Milton - Correspondence, Biographical Material, 1961-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rivers, Larry, 1960-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Rocklin, Ray, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rosofsky, Seymour, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Schlemowitz, Abram, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Schueler, Jon, 1954-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Seligmann, Kurt, 1942-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sievan, Maurice - Correspondence, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sievan, Maurice - Photographs of Sievan and his artwork, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Siskind, Aaron, 1959-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
  - Smith, Leon Polk, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Spaventa, George, 1960-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1967-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Thompson, Bob, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Tigerman, Stanley, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Travis, Peter, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Tworkov, Jack, 1957-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43-49)
  - Urry, Steven Jay, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Vergette, Nicholas, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Vicente, Estaban, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Vincente, Estaban, 1961-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Vincente, Estaban, 1963-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Waite, George, 1961-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Weber, Hugo, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Woelffer, Emerson, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Yampolsky, Phyllis, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Young, David, 1961-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 59-60)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - Printed Material, circa 1962-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - A-C, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - D-F, 1959-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - G, 1958-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - H-J, 1959-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - K-L, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - M-N, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - P, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - R-S, 1960-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Artists, Miscellaneous - T-W, 1959-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Oversized Ginzel, Roland from Box 1, Folder 34, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
  - Oversized Hunt, Richard from Box 1, Folder 55, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
- Business Records, 1961-1963; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 2
  Found here are a few invoices, correspondence, and notes.
  - Business Records, 1961-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 71)